Because violence for the more
experienced trader might be not only how
big it is but how it developed, the
speed at how it grew, right? So a lot of
us that are day trading and really
looking at the candles, they behave a
certain way, right? Some have every
stock has a very distinct personality.
And so when you see that bar after
multiple bars down, you might start to
see it jitter and then all of a sudden
that velocity starts to come and that's
that violence. And so sometimes if your
intuition is is there and you have the
experience, you might be able to like,
oh, you get that gut feeling, you jump
into the violence and it turns out to
even grow more
markets, speculation, and risk. This is
the Chat with Traders podcast.
>> Hey everyone, welcome back to Chat with
Traders. This is episode 309.
I'm Tessa doing this show with my
co-host Ian Cox. How's it going? How are
you? I hope you're doing well in every
way. And I hope you're also finding joy
in the little and simple things in life
to help keep you grounded no matter what
your circumstances are. Let's always try
to support and lift each other up. Okay,
trading is hard enough, right? Take care
of yourself. Our guest today is really
special to me for several reasons. And
one of the reasons why he's special to
me is because I've gotten to know him in
the past several years through the chat
traders community. And he's been one of
our influential members in the community
alongside a few others that we've
mentioned in the past. But today, this
particular trader's name is Diego Cortez
Lopez. Diego was basically raised on the
tennis courts from around age five.
Tennis was his passion in his young
life. And by the way, he's still very
young. Eventually though, a back injury
closed the door on him going pro. And so
by 16, he was coaching tennis,
successfully coaching private and group
lessons until 2020 hit. And then you
know what happened in 2020, right? Since
then, he's been living in Southeast Asia
from Bali and Vietnam. So, I guess you
can say he's a classic digital nomad
style American expat trader. He's one of
those 100% trading for a living traders
who are just hard to find that are
willing to interview. So, I guess we're
lucky. By the way, he's never missed an
open. Talk about dedication to one's
craft. Diego trades large cap stocks
using a rule-based approach that he
learned from his mentor Oliver, focusing
on certain support and resistance levels
and clean reversal signals and also very
clean charts. I mean simple simple
simple charts. I've seen them myself. He
trades mainly in the first hour of the
market open with tight stops and a 3:1
or better reward to risk ratio and
cutting risk fast over and over, proving
that disciplined execution matters more
than a high win rate. In this episode,
you'll also hear a few trading terms and
concepts from Oliver Veles's
methodology, which Diego has drawn from,
but over the years, he's also blended it
into his own trading approach. By the
way, Diego explains the strategies in
such a way that even without a chart or
visuals, you can imagine what he's
describing. So, pretty cool. Anyway,
let's get to it. Ladies and gentlemen,
we are so pleased to introduce Diego
Cortez Lopez. currently living in
Southeast Asia.
>> Well, first I'd like to welcome welcome
you to Chat with Traders.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah. And tell us a little bit about
your early uh childhood, kind of where
you grew up and um kind of what
interests you early on.
>> So, I was born in Mexico City, but I
grew up in uh Dallas, Texas. At a very
young age, I started playing tennis. Uh,
I've been playing tennis since I was
maybe 5 years old, somewhere around
that. Um, I'm 24 today. I'll be 25
September 7th, but so I've been playing
maybe 20 years. Um, I got to a point
where I was pretty close to playing
maybe professional. Who knows? I got
injured before I I could find out if I
could have made it. So I I acquired uh
quite a bit of discipline through sports
through tennis. I think uh that passion
then eventually led me to desiring to
find something else to get very good at
since tennis was something that I just
could not keep doing. Eventually I
started teaching uh tennis
young adults, adults, elderly
and uh I did that for a few years. How
old were you at that time when you were
teaching tennis? Uh
>> I think I started teaching around I was
16. So at the age of 16, I hit my I was
I think I was hitting my prime. You
know, 16 year olds by the time you're
16, you should know if you're going
professional or not. Um because most
professionals, they go professional
around 17, 18. So at that time, I was I
was pretty good. Um but my back injury
did not u permit me to to advance.
Um so I stopped playing tennis um that
much and uh I focused on teaching. Turns
out that teaching was a very very very
good uh business. started doing private
lessons, group lessons, and uh I did
that for a few years until COVID hit and
uh that killed the the whole business.
And I was like, "All right, well uh I
got plenty of money, plenty of savings.
I'm going to move out to some other
country." Chose Mexico. And I was there
for a while. Came back to the US midco
around 2021, I believe. then moved to to
Asia a little before COVID happened.
So late 2019.
>> Interesting. So you you moved to Asia
while you were still kind of figuring
out what you wanted to do or or you were
temporarily sidelined from the teaching
um tennis.
>> Yeah. So TW so 2020 killed the tennis
business. made some money the start of
2020, but late 2019
got into trading through some guy I met
in college and uh it was I got into
Robin Hood like everyone else does.
Bought my first stock, Tesla, Bitcoin,
and I think some penny stock. I forget
what it's called. And um early 2020
around March
or was it February or March that before
the big recovery is when I really got
into trading and um I think that was
during spring break of college and never
went back to college. I just dropped out
and I said I like this. This is really
really cool. So I'm going to go all in.
I had plenty of savings uh because of
tennis. So, I decided to move to Mexico
for a few months, tried it out, lost
everything through trading.
>> Tell us, let's let's get into the weeds
on that one. What um what were your
early kind of strategies and um what was
your style of trading early on?
>> Um it's a bit embarrassing. I I really
did not know what I was doing. Um, I
thought I did, of course, back in the
day, but I was, uh, so-called scalping,
going for one or two points, trading
futures. Um, futures was the cheapest
way to access the market cuz stocks was
too expensive. So, I was doing that,
scalping u micro micro minis. I I think
that's what they're called, right? I
forget. I haven't traded future in many
years. But yeah, I was scalping those,
trying to make something happen. I was
basically trying to short the lows of
previous days. So, I was shorting at
support and I was buying into
resistance. So, I had it the wrong way.
I should have been buying at support and
shorting at resistance,
>> but I didn't know any better. Um, so I
was getting smoked, lost nearly six
figures. Um, so that was that was pretty
painful. And then uh after Mexico after
losing all that money, I moved back to
the US, started the tennis business back
up. Did that for about six, seven
months, made a lot of money again.
Um, and then moved to Bali and I'm still
trading during these these times, right?
So I haven't missed a single open since,
>> you know, the start of 2020. And so
after losing that money, did you um did
you make any adjustments or were you
learning did you have like a mentor or
any how did you learn?
>> No, I I did not have any mentor. Um I
thought I could have learned this skill
on my own, but I was very wrong. Um I
didn't change anything. I thought that I
was around the neighborhood of being on,
you know, the on the right path, but I
was very wrong. Um it it took me so two
years and a half to find the the right
approach. I can't tell you exactly what
what was it 20
late 2022 that things started to turn
around. So two years and a half into my
trading.
>> Were you doing the same uh strategy of
of buying at resistance and then
shorting at support or uh any
modifications along the way? And and
what security you were trading? Futures.
Is that correct? Is that at that time?
>> Yes.
>> At that time still trading MNQ, MEES,
the Russell,
and uh I'm I'm scalping looking for
breakouts out of yesterday's highs or
yesterday lows. So, I would short the
low of yesterday hoping that it would
break down a lot lower just for it to
reverse on me and get smoked. Now, keep
in mind that my stop losses are very
small. So, any any movement will nick me
out and I'll lose, you know, 99%
of the time. So, I clearly did not know
what I was doing. And then, uh, I met um
through YouTube, I think in late 2022, I
found a a gentleman called Oliver Veles.
He's been trading for almost five
decades. Clearly, he knows what he's
talking about. Um, so I I gave it a shot
and uh it it did give me new eyes. I had
to unlearn everything I learned and um
it turns out that trading was actually a
lot a lot more simple than I could have
imagined. So just a basic risk
management, some decent odds and uh
yeah, so I I developed myself since 2022
on the right way and then uh I guess in
December I'll be trading for six years
more or less. So I'm still a baby in
this industry, you know, six years is
nothing.
>> So um let's dive into the new way of
trading. like what kind of a trader are
you in this new type of trading? Are you
a scalper or day trader or what?
>> So today um for the past 3 years and a
half or more or less um I've been
trading stocks. So I just trade the big
main stocks, you know, whatever is
popular. So Tesla, AMD, MU, Microsoft,
Meta, MSTR, um the big ones as long as
they have a low spread. And I do the
opposite of what I used to do in the
past. So I buy at support and I short at
resistance, have the appropriate
stop-loss, aim for a decent riskreward
and uh not worry too much about the win
rate cuz um you know back in the day
when I was scalping I I I believed that
I could achieve a nine out of 10 win
rate, eight out of 10 or even seven out
of 10 um which I was very wrong. Um, now
today with my six years of experience
and a lot of losing, I believe that not
everyone is capable of producing a 70%
win rate. I think that is
extraordinarily high. But I'm sure
there's people out there, you know,
there's always a Djokovic or a Michael
Jordan or something like that. But I'm
not that guy, you know? I'm not that
smart.
>> I'm not that that good. But I can
reproduce a 30% 40% win rate. So as long
as my win rate is uh 30 40% and the
riskreward makes sense, right? Those two
key factors um you can be profitable.
>> So let's dive into
>> uh let's dive into uh kind of what you
look for say to go long or go short like
what are the characteristics
of uh of what what does a chart look
like to you? So all I focus on is the
daily. All I focus is at the daily. I
look at any major support. So any daily
high. So yesterday for example,
yesterday let's say call it uh the spy.
Yesterday's high and yesterday's low. If
it had a violent bounce off the lows,
right, it created a very violent major
bounce, then I'll consider it a strong
support. And if today opens and it
reaches that level, if it gives me, for
example, a tail bar, I'll consider a
long. As long as the the the entry and
the stop is small enough to give me a
decent reward, then I'll take it. And I
just have to be right three times out of
10. Uh so when you're looking at support
then it doesn't you don't look at uh the
preceding um weeks or months to see oh
wow this level of support is really good
going back a number of months. So that
would influence my desire to maybe
increase my position at when it gets
back down to that support or do you just
totally ignore all prior history prior
than the day before? So, it can go back
a few weeks as long as it's obvious to
the eye. So, it has to be obvious. If
you're if you're making it up and you're
guessing and you're trying to convince
yourself that it might be, it's probably
not. So,
>> everything is is is a self-fulfilling
prophecy, you could say. So, as long as
it's obvious that it's a support, then
it's probably going to play out most of
the time. Um, you don't want to be tra
trading random support levels off of a,
you know, one minute time frame cuz
you're probably going to get smoked most
of the time. But if you're looking at
those more important ones that maybe so
institutions or whatever big money is
looking at, whatever that you want to
call it, um, they work most of the time.
So daily support and resistance, that's
good. If I don't find anything off the
daily, I'll go down to a hourly, right,
to find some key support level um or
resistance. But most of the time, the
daily is always available. I trade
usually around 10 stocks. So, there's
always something available. But the
strategy doesn't work well in trending
markets. So, for example, today,
September 5, uh this morning the spy
sold off pretty heavily. you know,
trying to catch a falling knife is
probably not going to work out today.
But other days when we're, you know, a
little bit more calm, just ranging, um,
it's a good time.
>> I see. So, you're looking to, uh, play
the, um, what, overbought, oversold
conditions within a a cycle. Uhhuh.
>> Yep. Yep. Yep. Yeah. Mhm.
>> So, I really want, for example, today,
um, let's say the spy sold off for the
first 30 minutes and there's just, you
know, on a 5minute chart, there's just
10 red candles in a row. That's
obviously overextended. It's too much.
So, what I would look for is a buy
event. A buy event to me would be a nice
little tail bar. As long as it's obvious
to the eye that it is a tailbar, not too
big because you don't want the risk to
be too big, not too small because you
don't want to it needs to be bullish
enough, right? And go for a 3 one, four
one, but minimum 2 to one on the bounce.
>> So, you really want it overextension,
oversold into support
>> over I see. And what uh what time frame
are you looking at um on your charts?
>> Five minute. That's the main one I look
at.
>> Okay. five minute chart. So when it
looks to you so it signifies that um the
correction is over when you have what a
reversal bar is that it
>> Yeah. So people what do they call it?
They call it tail bars.
Oliver calls them 180s, wide range bars.
There's a bunch of names to it, but any
any reversal bar, any reversal event um
that qualifies for a potential um long
as long as the location is good, right?
So, major support levels.
>> Uh-huh. What if the volume is really
light on on the bounce? Does that
influence you not to go long because
it's the the volume's weak or how do you
look at that?
>> I don't look at volume.
>> Um so, I I could not tell you. Um, I've
learned how to use it, but in my
day-to-day trading, I don't use it. Um,
I keep it very simple as long as it's
very oversold. At least, you know,
multiple bars in a row of the same
color. So, you can imagine it, you know,
spy selling off 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 nine red
bars in a row. If you were short, you
would probably start to, you know,
tighten up your trailing um approach. So
a pullback would be imminent right after
such a move. So I'd use the 5m minute
and in order to reduce my risk I'll use
a smaller time frame such as the 2
minute or even the 1 minute to try to
really nail down my entry and find a
appropriate stop. And uh a lot of times
I might be able to find a very nice
entry with a very nice stop that could
potentially reward me with 3:1, 4:1,
5:1, sometimes even more.
>> And how do you calculate I mean how do
you uh what's your target price to get
out when you say 3:1 4:1 uh ratio? What
what kind of retracement back up in this
case are you expecting? Um the
retracement that I'm expecting is no
more than a third of the move up. So
>> one third of the decline. So one third
retracement back up.
>> Uhhuh. Uhhuh.
>> Yeah. So I think uh people call those
Fibonacci levels or something like that.
>> But I just imagine it's just massive u
massive move down a bounce to the one-/3
mark. That is the most I should expect.
Now can it go a lot further? Sure. So
that would be the home run. But I need
to make sure that my profit take is at
the 1/3 mark. And by that moment, I
should be able to achieve at least one
to two. Um, if I can get more, then
perfect.
>> So when you're looking at the uh
potential reversal and then you get one
one reversal bar, does it matter to you
or how much would it impact your
decision to go long uh if it's a violent
uh retracement like like a what we would
call an elephant bar? Yeah. So, if the
retracement happens very violently
without me being in it, then I'll wait
for the price to come back down to where
I wanted to get in
>> and then put the stop at the low of day.
So, imagine the big move down, violent
retracement. It hasn't hit the one-/ird
mark yet. Or maybe it did. But if it
bounce, if it drops back into that area
of that violent retracement, it could
still be potentially a good buy for
another move up
>> to that same one-/ird mark. Does that
make sense? So, it's like a second a
second attempt to get a second chance to
get in the trade.
>> I see. And u in one of your videos, you
referred to this, I believe, what was
called the gift zone. Is that
>> That's what it is. And so what does this
what does this uh bar look like? I mean
the this violent bar, how does it
compare to the other bars so that
traders can can identify uh this when
this happens?
>> It it just has to be a lot bigger than
everything else to the left. So it it
has to be obvious.
>> It has to be very obvious. Again, if
you're guessing, if you're doubting,
then it's probably not big. So it it has
to be a lot bigger than everything to
the left. Um if you were to ask a child
to, you know, circle the big bars,
that's how it was taught. Highlight the
big bars. That's how Val taught us. And
uh
>> it's just that simple. If it's big, if
it's obvious, then you know it's a
violent bar.
>> Um now you can go more in depth, right?
Because violence for the more
experienced trader might be not only how
big it is but how it developed, right?
The speed at how it grew, right? So a
lot of us that are day trading and
really looking at the candles, they
behave a certain way, right? Some have
every stock has a very distinct
personality. And so when you see that
bar, you know, let's say after multiple
move, multiple bars down, you might
start to see it jitter and then all of a
sudden that velocity starts to come and
that's that violence. And so sometimes
if your intuition is is there and you
have the experience, you might be able
to like, oh, you get that gut feeling,
you jump into the violence and it turns
out to even grow more. It's hard to
explain.
>> I see. And so, but you said earlier that
um normally you you wait uh even though
you see the the violent bar, you wait
for it to retrace. How often does it
retrace and and how often have you found
that it just continues to go on go on up
and and you missed out on the trade?
>> I I found it to personally from my
stats, it's 50/50. It's 50/50. So
sometimes um if you're not in the trade,
right, if you don't nail the entry um
and it goes without you very violently,
it might just go straight up and hit the
profit target. And sometimes it'll
bounce violently, pull back, give you
another chance to get in and then the
move happens. But um you know, it's
50/50. And how often do you see these
elephant bars with any one particular
stock or does it high vary significantly
depending on the the stock you're
looking at?
>> It happens every every day. Um okay
every day multiple times at least 10 20
times a day. So it it's that that
specific event the very large bar um
it's everywhere. Um, you can
>> with the same stock
>> w with the same stock or do you need to
be looking at dozens of stocks
>> with with the same stock and can happen
of course depending on the time frame
>> it can happen multiple times a day. So
if you were to look at the spy today on
the five minute I mean there's multiple
large bars
um even on the 15minute there's multiple
large bars. So today, September 5th, for
the people listening. Um, but yeah,
there's there's multiple large bars,
multiple of them, you could call it.
Okay, this is this move is oversold.
It's exhausted. So yeah, now the
important ones are obviously the ones
that uh originate the origin of the move
and the ones that are at the very end,
right? The exhausting part. Do you trade
um mainly in the morning session or
throughout the day or have you found any
particular time times during the day
that you prefer over others?
>> Um I do best after the first 20 minutes
go by. So I'll usually trade only the
first 60 minutes. That's it.
>> Oh why why is that? I mean what makes
the first 60 minutes um better for you
than say the rest of the day?
So you I well one I'm in Asia so I have
no
>> you know interest in I want to go to
sleep um early um
>> but majority of the volatility is in the
first 60 minutes first 90 minutes so um
if I can't get the job done by the first
60 minutes um I don't want to be there
so that's just me
>> uh again also So more participants are
in the first 60 minutes, right? So for
my events to work, I need people
trading, right? I need the big money to
be um there. And so if I if I don't have
participants, then there's not going to
be follow through on the trades that I'm
taking, right? So I need that
institutional
participation. I could you could say
>> do you look at uh moving averages uh and
their potential uh aid in helping you go
long or go short?
>> Yeah, I use the 200 moving average, the
simple moving average and the 20 to keep
it simple. If the price is above the 20
and the 200, you're in a bullish state.
If your price is below the 20 and the
200, you're obviously in a bearish
state. Um, if the 20 and the 200 get too
separated, right, then you could assume
that you've been trending for quite a
while and be careful going long now. Um,
that's what we call a wide state um or a
trending state. Wide state. A wide state
can always get wider. So, be very
careful trying to go against the trend.
But that's why I say that uh um when I'm
going short, I'll take a short at a good
location that has decent odds of
producing a reversal.
>> Okay. Describe that to us. At a good
location, like what was it? What would
it look like on the chart and with the
the moving averages and so that people
can imagine what you're talking about?
>> Imagine um imagine I don't say Tesla.
It's been in a range for the whole week.
It's Friday and um right off the open
you get 10 green bars in a row up into
let's say the major high of the week
right which happens to be let's say two
days ago right on a Wednesday and that
Wednesday happened to be a very violent
drop from the top so the origin of the
move was violent so I can assume that if
Friday's move, which is right now green.
We're 10 bars up. If we can get to that
Wednesday high, right, which is just a
simple resistance, I could expect I
could predict that there's going to be
some sort of reaction, probably a drop.
The majority of the time, new highs
fail, so I'm going to bet that there's
going to be some sort of reversal. So,
let's say now we're 15 green 15 green
bars in a row, and we get that nice
topping tail bar. Um, that's a short
opportunity, right? Short it. Let's hope
that the risk is appropriate and uh the
riskreward makes sense and go for it.
Now, I would say that for most traders,
they should aim to achieve a 30% win
rate. I think that's reproducible.
That's realistic for the majority of the
industry. I think a lot of people go
many years trying to achieve uh
unrealistic unrealistic uh statistics
that it's just it's just not going to
happen. So 30% with a 3 4:1
um math is going to make money for you.
Now it's not cute, it's not impressive,
but it's reproducible.
>> Yeah. Where do you set your stops? Is it
or have you heard of it being common for
traders to set their stops just slightly
above the very top of that resistance
level and it creates a uh an area for um
trader other traders or manipulators to
do stop-loss hunting to blow out those
those last little stops. And so where do
you place your stop? So if the tail bar
appears like I said after 15 green bars
the tail bar appears I short at the tail
bar at the low of the tail bar and the
stop will go above the tail bar. If I
get shaken out right the tail bar gets
taken out and let's say maybe one bar
high or two more bars proceed after that
and then another tail bar appears then
I'll give it a second shot. But this
it's only I'll only give it two chances.
Um, and shakeouts happen. I just have to
to re-enter. Um, and I there are
re-entry approaches that I that I take.
Um, but uh I I don't like to to give
myself a wide stop. I'd rather be wrong
more often. Um, and and have good risk
management.
>> I I see. So, where you place the stop is
not based on a percentage. It's based on
on uh where it be just above the um the
tail bar, meaning you're you're um
putting your stop just above the the
last highest level of resistance that
you saw.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And uh the monetary stop is the
most important. So every every trader
should have either a percent stop or a
dollar amount stop. Mhm. Um, do you
place much importance when the uh 200
day moving average is aligned or
compressed together with the 20-day
moving average uh when you see these uh
elephant bars appear? In other words, do
you are there scenarios where you see a
confluence of events that are so
compelling that you greatly increase
your position size or uh how does
position sizing work for you?
So position sizing um for me it it's
changed over the years. A few years ago
I had the approach where I would have my
light size, medium size, heavy size. Um
but nowadays um since my win rate is a
lot lower. It's around 35%. I keep my
position size relatively the same since
I just don't know which which trade is
going to be the winner. So all my
position sizing is the same. I don't
want for me to position size lightly and
then because of the randomness of the
market, it ends up being a mega trade
like today. Today my the trade that I
accidentally position sized too lightly
ended up being the biggest move of the
day. Why? I couldn't tell you. The other
trade was the better setup, but today
this one just happened to to be the main
move. It's it's too random for me to um
honestly say yeah like I know I should
be position sizing very heavy here. I
just over the years I I can I I admit I
just cannot manage to be right seven out
of 10 times. So I'd rather keep that 30%
win rate 35 and position size um the
best I can. So, let's say today um I
take a trade where the risk on the tail
bar might be $50, but I get a better
entry and I can size in a little bit
heavier. My risk might be very tiny, but
by the time it starts moving my way, I'm
heavily sized in while still losing $50
or less, and that turns out to be a big
winner. So, entries are very important.
Um, do you do any uh journaling?
>> Um, yeah. I journal every day on my uh I
have a a WhatsApp group chat with myself
in it and I'll just screenshot the trade
and put it there and uh but uh I don't
journal anymore. Um I used to journal a
few years ago but no, not anymore. Um I
think I
>> I know what I'm doing today so it's just
uh
>> second nature. I show up one minute
before the open. I don't really trade
the first 20 minutes, so it doesn't
really matter. Um, it's a it's a very uh
slow and uh what would you say?
Nonchalant. It's just laidback.
>> Uhhuh.
>> But um it's become like walking. So it's
it's easy now.
>> What do you um what's your opinion? uh
when traders some traders say that they
like to look at multiple time frames uh
many time frames to to really nail down
you know is this move sustainable uh so
they'll look at maybe the 2 minute 5 you
know 1530 hour to try to get a a
comprehensive look at um the quality of
of the move you place much value in that
or just looking at a 2-minut or 5 minute
is sufficient for you
>> for for the beginner I would say to just
stick to only one time frame and learn
to read that cuz most of the time
beginners they they look at too many
things and they get overwhelmed and um
they they don't master one thing. So
when I first started, I focused only on
the 2-minut and I I became profitable on
the 2-minut and then I added on, you
know, the 5m minute, the 15-minute, the
hourly, and the daily and use those as
confluence. Right now, if you're more
experienced, then you'll know how to use
the 15. The more confluences you get,
the better. But for the beginner, I'd
stick to one thing. Um, too much is all
is usually not good. Does uh anything in
the pre-market activity influence your
trading at all or do you place much
value uh looking at the pre-market?
>> I don't look at pre-market. Uh I have
pre-market turned off. So I only have
regular trading hours on. The first
thing I'll I'll pay attention is uh
yesterday's high and yesterday's low.
And if it's if it is like I said a
violent uh drop from the yesterday's
high, then I'll consider as a zone to go
short. Um, but I don't look at
pre-market. No.
>> Um, let's go back to the uh the gift
zones. So, you say about half the time
uh when you get an elephant bar on a
reversal, it'll continue on uh in that
direction and roughly the other half
it'll experience somewhat of a
correction back into the gift zone,
allowing you to get a better uh purchase
price. How do you I mean when it starts
to fall after it makes the elephant bar
to correct back is there a other bar
like a somewhat of a reversal to know
that you look at so that it doesn't keep
falling uh that it maintains some level
of support within that narrow um within
that minute or two minutes time frame.
There's there's no
let's say you have a elephant bar wide
range bar off the five minute and it's
retracing back into the gift, right?
There's no way to really know that this
is going to be the one that ends up
dropping even lower and stops you out
and continues down or it's the one that
goes higher. It's very random. Um the
the only guideline that I do have is
that ideally you don't want the majority
of the bar to be removed. And so you
could use let's say 80% of it. 80% of
the the large bar. If 80% of it gets
removed, you can assume that most of its
power is not holding up and it's over,
>> right? Mhm.
>> Um, but for the beginner, I just keep
the stop at the very low and you gain
that experience of three. Oh. Oh. So
over time looks like at 80% of the the
bar being removed, usually it fails. But
there are times where it retraces near
the lows and then violently turns around
again. So the guideline is as long as it
doesn't take out 80% of it. Um, if you
want to be more aggressive, the halfway
mark would be it, but I think that's too
much.
>> So, in the years you've been trading,
um, and I don't know how many other
traders you have met or or talked to,
but is there have you witnessed uh the
common types of mistakes that traders
make both for yourself and other people
that you've you know? Yeah, I think um
off the top of my head, I think one of
the most common mistakes is starting off
with sculping.
I think that's that's a big mistake.
Attempting to have a high win rate. I
think that's um big mistake because it
just it takes so much skill to maintain
such a high level of accuracy with good
risk management to to stay profitable.
Um I personally don't know anyone. Well,
that's a lie. Of of course, my mentors,
you know, but they've been trading for
four, five decades. So, but other than
that, um people have been trading for
about my time, six, 10 years. I don't
know anyone that has such a high win
rate, um and is scalping for a living.
Um most of them are doing 30 40%
and they have 3:1 4:1 riskrewards and
and they're doing well. So starting off
with scalping, um I think that's a big
mistake because in the long run for the
beginner, they never learn to hold on to
a winner. Um they cut their winners so
so quickly and um just from pure human
nature, they they hold the losers and
the opposite happens, right? So the
profitable guy, he's cutting the loser
quickly and holding on to the big
winner. um the not profitable guy and
the losing trader. He's uh of course
taking it too early and holding it too
long, the loser. So it's literally the
opposite. Um very funny.
>> Uh it's uh as beginners we do the we do
things backwards. So
>> Right. Right. So, what are the
indicators for you uh given that you're
trading in in a short time frame to hold
on to your winners longer? And do you
ever come across situations where things
are going so good during the day that uh
you decide to hold it overnight?
>> I've never hel No, I don't hold trades
overnight. Um I'm always out of the
trades before
um the hour ends
um the first hour. But what what keeps
me holding a trade is um is just seeing
those violent bars
continue and continue and continue. So
let's say I'm looking at the two-minute
chart.
If there's just consecutive
medium to large size bars, just
non-stop, I'll just trail my stop at a
decent distance using perhaps a moving
average or a bar by bar under every bar
until I get um trailed out. But usually
I'm I'm able to achieve a 2:1 almost
right off the bat. So from my entry, 2:1
is relatively close because my stops are
pretty small. Um, so I like to see the
trade pop violently in my direction. By
the time I hit two to one, I'll get my
first profit take and continue to trail
out.
>> In in one of your videos, uh, you
mentioned about uh good experience and
bad experience trades. Um, what are
they? So like uh like a like I was doing
uh many years ago back in 2020 shorting
at support and buying into resistance.
Um and believing that you're doing the
right thing. Um a lot of people are very
convinced
that by using this this this this this
this generating good experience and most
of the time um they're creating a lot of
uh a bad experience that it it makes you
go backwards in your journey rather than
forwards. And uh I've met a lot of dudes
that have been trading 15 20 years and
um not to be rude, but um they're very
bad. They're they've gone completely
backwards
um just because of the false beliefs
that they have uh um generated like
myself. Buying into support, scalping,
trying to achieve 90% win rates, holding
on to losers and believing that it's
going to bounce while holding it for
days or even months. And these are not
things that generate good experience.
What if they come back and say, "But uh
these trades are as long as it's
profitable, isn't that a good experience
trade?" I mean, aren't all trades, uh,
potentially good experience trades
because you're learning something from
each trade, whether you're making money
or losing money, right?
>> Everything, every loss can be a good
experience as long as you break down the
loss and you understand why you lost.
But if you don't break it down and
analyze it and stay arrogant and and
tell yourself that it's fine, it's fine.
It doesn't matter and continue to do
those same bad habits. I don't know
where the saying comes from, but I think
someone says that uh the definition of
insanity is doing the same thing over
and over expecting a different result.
Um, so that was me many years ago losing
in the same way, expecting a different
result, thinking that I'm getting
better, but I was going backwards.
>> What is a trap zone? And what can we uh
make some good trades in this in this
trap zone?
>> Yeah. Um, the trap zone as I was taught
by is just um being stuck between a
major high and major low. Um, and in
this case with the definition of the
trap zone, it's usually using
yesterday's um, last 45 minutes of data.
But the trap zone really can be at any
time anywhere. So if you're
consolidating in a range, in a tight
range or mediumsiz range, that could be
a trap zone. So, you usually don't want
to be trading inside of a consolidation
or ranging
um market cuz you're going to get
smoked.
>> Um now, if you're very good, then you
can trade the range, right? Um but yeah,
usually you want to try to stay away
from that. Um, I personally prefer
ranging markets, obviously big ranges
because I want to be, you know, off
support and resistance, but on a smaller
time frame, of course, you're on a
twominut, you don't want to be trading
inside of a tight range. That's uh not a
good idea.
>> So, uh, share with us a little bit u how
has your trading performance been over
the years or how how has it kind of
evolved and fluctuated over the years?
Yeah. Um, 20 2022
was fantastic. 2023 was was even better.
2024 was my best year. Um, 2025, this
year has been slow. Um, but, you know, I
I still think I'm a I'm a baby in the
industry, so a lot to learn. Um, but
it's it's over overall it's been um a
line up, right? It's exponential lineup.
So, it's good. Every month is very
difficult. Every month, every week is
very challenging. So, a lot more
experience is needed. Um, I have um
mentors that are green every single day,
but these guys have been trading 30, 40
or even 50 years, like the less. So, of
course, sure they have two or three red
days per year, but I mean, these guys
are incredibly incredibly skilled.
>> And you've been living uh uh whereabouts
in Asia for for some years now.
>> Yeah. Um I lived in uh Bali for for a
while. Um I lived in the north of
Vietnam on a city called Nachang. And uh
I've been living in a small island in
the south of Vietnam for for quite a
while now called Fukwok.
So it's uh it's a very beautiful island.
Uh it's definitely you got to look it
up. Very very very beautiful. I think it
has some of the most beautiful beaches
in the world.
>> Wow. Fantastic. Sounds like you're
living the life.
>> Yeah, it's nice.
>> Excuse the last interruption here. This
is Tessa. We hope you're enjoying this
episode so far. If you love the podcast,
please give Chat with Traders the best
review you can on whatever platform
you're listening from. This will help us
to keep the episodes coming. Also, if
you haven't subscribed to our email
list, please hop on to
chatwithtraders.com
and click on subscribe so we can keep
you posted of information that may be of
importance. Thank you. Now, back to the
chat with our guest.
>> Yeah. Uh uh I wanted to go back to um
you mentioned that u some of these guys
that you know trading in a similar style
that you do uh are green overwhelming
majority of the time um except for a few
days here and there throughout the year.
What what do you think they do
differently qualitatively? what what
makes them uh super profitable u much
more than say the average trader who
follows their same system like what
could we do different to uh get their to
their level of experience to their level
of performance
>> I would say that it's uh the psychology
the psychology the ability to to reduce
risk so so incredibly well um they're
They're they're very very good at um
losing very small amounts. Um that's
very impressive. And um I also think
that the the size of your account does
matter. Um I think um especially
depending on the style that you have.
There are traders that are able to to
pyramid into trades um and get
themselves out of a nasty trade and turn
it into a winner. And of course, the
more money you have, the more you can
pyramid and and uh damage control and
and get out of a a losing position. Um
but of course, that also takes an
incredible amount of skill. Um but yeah,
I I think it really comes down to to
psychology. um an amazing ability to to
lose well. Uh incredible risk
management.
Um they're great losers. That's that's I
think that's what it is.
>> Uhhuh. Uhhuh. Have you uh shared uh your
passion of trading or been able to teach
anyone else uh to trade during these
years in uh Asia?
>> Uh with Tessa when I met her um I don't
know when we met. I think it was uh
three years ago. Was it three years ago?
something like that. Um, I was able to
to teach um some people that are still
with me today. They're my some of my
closest friends, so I talk with them um
um pretty pretty regularly and um
sometimes we trade together. Um so
they're great friends and um most of us
do trade the same approach and uh it
it's it's been good. Um I love those
guys. They're my friends and it's hard
to make friends in this industry
sometimes.
>> Uh so to wrap things up, uh what do you
struggle with most as a trader?
>> Um I think uh for me is is obviously the
losing. Um I I don't like losing. Um
>> I come from a um from a very successful
career, I guess, in tennis where I was
very accustomed to always winning. Um
but uh it it's a everyday struggle to be
okay with losing going on sometimes 10
10 trade losing streaks that can happen
right uh but staying staying with the
method staying with the approach and uh
sticking through those uh those tough
times is it's just part of the math
right
>> uh so are you um do you feel that you're
now um at a place where you're
comfortable with your process, kind of
your life. Um is there anything that
you're looking forward to next?
>> My my main focus today is uh obviously
trading and investing
um a lot. Everything that I make, I try
to invest it all and uh enjoy my life,
have fun, not focus too much on money.
So yeah, it's good. Great.
>> Things are good.
>> Fantastic. Diego. Uh, Diego, thanks for
coming on to Chat with Traders.
>> Thank you so much.
>> Oh, hi there. Thanks for sticking
through the end and I hope you enjoyed
Ian's chat with Diego. So, if you have a
few more minutes, feel free to stay on
for my brief chat with Diego. Take care.
So, regarding tennis, do you still play
tennis for fun or
>> Yeah, I found a uh a golf club. There's
a what do they call it? uh country club.
There's a country club like uh five
minutes away from here by the beach.
It's like a big resort and they have
tennis courts, pickle ball courts, golf.
We go there. Me and my girl go there
pretty often.
>> Yeah.
>> Um I'm trying to go to the beach every
day cuz you know you get used to it so
you stop going. But um we're going there
as often as we can every other day.
>> Yeah. Yeah,
>> some days we have lazy days, but yeah,
still playing.
>> Well, that's great. It's great that
you're still um somehow involved in in
your passion of tennis, your your very
first passion, right? Tennis. Um
>> yeah,
>> because of your tennis background and
you said that you you taught tennis. I
feel like it's really reflected in your
explanations, you know, on the way you
trade, especially I was part of your,
you know, private group, your your
trading group, and I just remember just
the way that you you explain things on
the chart and kind of your approach
based on Oliver's uh methods. It was
just so clear to me. And one of the the
uh things I remember that I use every
day in my trading is the trap zone. Um,
I think I mentioned that to you. I I
swear I use that that is so helpful for
me. Just that one thing I can remember
and I can use every day to either stay
out of it or if I go in it be really
really um cautious. But that is um
something I use every day. So um I just
want to thank you for for sharing that
with me. Um
>> yeah.
>> And also there's something that you said
that really was really interesting. You
never missed an open at the market open
since you started trading?
>> Yeah, I've never missed an open.
>> How do you do that?
>> Um I think I've made um trading always
my priority. It's it's been my ultimate
passion. Um even though I think it's one
of the most frustrating and difficult
activities, but also very rewarding. I
love it a lot. I don't want to miss any
open. I feel like missing an open is uh
especially since I don't have a a job,
right? I don't have anything else to do.
So, there's no excuse for sleeping in
or, you know, being out doing something
that I shouldn't be doing. Like, I need
to be there for the open. Yeah.
>> Especially cuz one day I want to
>> be able to say like I'm a true
professional. Um and so I I should
dedicate myself as much as I can. It's
uh I would say I'm still in my
university years. Um late university
years.
>> I I feel like you're already a I feel
like you're a professional already,
Diego. But you're so humble and
>> it's a humility that really um is, you
know, is is what brought you here, I
think.
>> Um so you mentioned I remember you
talking to me and you taught your
girlfriend how to trade as well. Is that
true?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. She uh she still
trades almost every day. She's picked up
other hobbies. So, she uh she loves
cooking. She loves baking. She loves uh
um making dresses and working with clay.
So, um as as long as I can fund all her
hobbies and she's happy and entertained,
I'm happy. If she wants to trade, uh she
can trade. if she wants to do whatever
she wants to do. Um, you know, I'll be
there for to support her. But, um, yeah,
every now and then she's trading for
fun.
>> That's amazing. Um, it's like it's like
you guys are partners in crime.
>> Yeah.
>> Trading. That's amazing. Um, and I think
it's great that, um, you know, she has
other hobbies, too, because honestly, if
I were to just trade and that's the only
thing I did, I I don't think I can
handle it. It's Yeah, I got to have
other things. Um,
>> yeah,
>> let's see. There's a one. Okay. Trading
from a 13-inch laptop screen. That's
another very unique. We've never like
I've never had a guest on the show that
trades from a laptop. one laptop, small
laptop. Is that driven by just the
lifestyle that you have or convenience
or or simplicity? What why is that?
>> Um, it's um well, I I first started off
trading off of uh four monitors. So, I
had the laptop and then two ultra wide
monitors. So, that's four. So, it was it
was a ridiculous setup, but I was losing
money in a cool way. And and then
eventually I learned uh Oliver's
approach. I realized that it was so
simple that I really only needed to look
at one screen, one time frame. Um so my
laptop was all I needed. And uh I travel
a lot. I travel quite a few times per
year. So, um I' I've refined um my
approach to be simple enough that I only
need one screen um and that's it. If I
could trade off my phone, um obviously
if if it was swing trading, not day
trading, day trading, I I definitely
need my my uh hot keys to be quick,
>> but um I can analyze any chart off of a
a phone. I mean, you don't need much for
reading a chart. Of course, trading, you
definitely need your your hot keys,
right?
>> To be quick.
>> 13 in. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Um, final question. Well, you mentioned
something I think is really important
about community um that you know when
when we had the chat with Traders
community uh open at the time and that's
how I met you actually is through the
community. I'm just so glad that you
came into our community because I feel
like you shared so much, you know, and
with other um community members and like
you said, you became friends with some
of them even to this day and that is
just so important because trading is
just by n by its nature is just so
lonely, right?
>> Yeah. Yeah. We're all still keeping in
touch. Um, I'm so grateful that you guys
made that community. It was uh it was u
life-changing at least for me. Um, good
friends, good experiences, and uh, it's
hard to find communities like that. Like
I said, it's hard to make friends. So
hopefully one day you guys make another
one cuz making friends is hard here.
>> Yeah. Well, no promises, but yeah,
that's always a possibility that in the
future we could reopen the community.
Um, yeah, just so glad that you're still
in touch with us, Diego. And yeah,
thanks for coming on the show.
>> Thank you so much. I really do
appreciate it.
>> You've reached the end of this episode
of Chat with Traders, but rest assured,
there are more episodes loaded with real
market insight and zero hype on the way
soon. So, to stay updated with each
great new release, subscribe to the
podcast in iTunes. and we'd love it if
you'd leave a rating and review. We'll
catch you next time on Chat with
Traders.
[Music]